Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is דף ט. daf
Tet. We pick up
very bottom of ח עמוד ב Chet Amud Bet and we are
discussing here מקום פטור. makom patur. And let's take a look, five
lines from the bottom. אמר מר, Amar Mar, so going back to
the penultimate point in the תוספתא Tosefta we've been focusing
on, ובלבד שלא יטול מבעל הבית ונותן לעני מעני ונותן לבעל הבית.
u-velvad she-lo yitohl mi-ba'al ha-bayit ve-noten le-ani mi-ani ve-noten le-ba'al ha-bayit. So
you have this ledge and or threshold or whatever, and it is
less than four by four, so it's a מקום פטור. makom patur.
So you can put from the house onto it and vice versa,
or from the רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim onto it and vice versa,
but do not use it as a way of getting from the
house into the רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim or רשות reshus into the
house by doing a little stopover. That would be a problem that
even though each step is acceptable, nevertheless, it's going to easily lead
to going straight from רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim to רשות היחיד. reshus
ha-yachid. ואם נטל ונתן, ve-im natal ve-natan, but if you did do
this, now this is imagining a person is on this ledge. So
he is taking from the owner and then or giving it to
the עני, ani, or taking from the עני ani and giving it
to the owner. So they're all involved in this. שלשתן פטורים, shloshtan
pturim, all three of them are exempt. Now one way of explaining
why all three of them are exempt is the same reason why
if it's like the משנה, mishna, as the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit
and the עני ani equally participate, they're exempt because they've each done
half of it. But this assumes like it's a more than that,
not that they're exempt because it went through the מקום פטור. makom
patur. So even if the guy in the middle in the מקום
פטור makom patur picked it up of one hand and put it
on the other, everybody is exempt because it went through the מקום
פטור. makom patur. So גמרא gemara is going to question this. Let's
take a look. גמרא gemara says, לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבא, leima tehavi
tiyuvta de-Rava,
let's say this is a contradiction to רבא, Rava, דאמר רבא, de-amar
Rava, because רבא Rava said, המעביר חפץ מתחלת ארבע לסוף ארבע, ha-ma'avir
chefetz mi-tchilas arba le-sof arba, so he imagines not from רשות היחיד
reshus ha-yachid to רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim but four אמות amos in
רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, somebody moves an object from the beginning of
four אמות amos to outside of four אמות amos ברשות הרבים, be-reshus
ha-rabim, אף על פי שהעבירו דרך עליו חייב, af al pi she-he'eviro
derech alav chayav,
although he did it over him or through him, he is חייב.
chayav. Now
why would I have thought otherwise? So the keyword is what דרך
עליו derech alav means. רש"י Rashi says what it means is 'al'
literally in terms of on top of, and what the person did,
he picked it up four אמות, amos, he brought it ten טפחים
tefachim off of רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim and then he put it
down outside four אמות. amos. So the issue is in the middle
it went through a space that was מקום פטור. makom patur. Okay,
so in a way it's similar to a question the גמרא gemara
had, you know, חנות לפלטיא דרך סתו, chanut le-palatya derech stav, going
through a כרמלית, karmelit, except this is going through a מקום פטור.
makom patur. And the גמרא gemara says look, you went through a
מקום פטור makom patur and you're חייב. chayav. So how is it
any different than the guy on the ledge when one guy standing
on the ledge takes from the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit and gives
to the עני? ani? So what if it went through מקום פטור?
makom patur? You should still be חייב. chayav. That's the גמרא'ס gemara's
question. תוספות Tosfos says דרך עליו derech alav doesn't mean on top
of him. It just means in front of him. And that what
you might have thought is if I'm standing in one place and
I'm passing an object in front of me and then putting it
down, the fact that I'm holding it for a moment right in
front of me is like it's stationary. You know, if I'm holding
something right in front of me even if I'm in the process
of moving it, when it gets to be right in front of
me it's like it stopped. I don't know, that's what you might
have thought. But that's at least what תוספות Tosfos says, it doesn't
mean that necessarily is going higher than ten. Either way the גמרא
gemara says how is that different than the guy on the ledge?
So
the גמרא gemara has a very simple answer.
התם לא נח הכא נח. hatam lo nach hacha nach. Fine, רבא'ס
Rava's case, it went through the air space, or according to תוספות
Tosfos it went in front of you, but it didn't stop. So
even though it goes through the air space of a מקום פטור
makom patur in front of you, it didn't stop, so you're חייב.
chayav. Here if the guy standing in a מקום פטור makom patur
picked it up and without stopping moved it through his space and
put it down in the other hands of the עני, ani, you
would be חייב. chayav. The reason here we're saying פטור patur is
because you stopped. He brings it to his ledge and puts it
down, and then he picks it up and then he gives it
to the next one. So there you're obviously פטור patur because it's
two separate acts and each one you're פטור, patur, each one actually
by itself מותר, mutar, רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim to מקום פטור, makom
patur, מקום פטור makom patur to רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, but combined
it's a problem because you will come to go straight from one
to the other without stopping in the middle. Yes, ארי? Ari?
Wasn't there a case yesterday where once it was like the beehive
that was falling down?
That's when when it came to rest it remained higher. Here, so
if not only did you pass it through מקום פטור, makom patur,
but when you put it in רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim part of
it remained up above ten טפחים, tefachim, you would be... But here
the point is where it was in the middle doesn't matter. It
started in a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, it ended fully in רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim. Sometime in the middle it was in some other
zone, but you know what? It never stopped in that other zone,
then you're going to be חייב. chayav. Okay, is that difference clear?
Yeah. Okay.
Two comments: one is there is no חידוש chiddush whatsoever and it's
a completely useless statement. I do not think so. And the other
is על גבי al gabei never means in front of
you, that would be לפניו. lefanav. Okay, so why does תוספות Tosafot
say על גבי al gabei means in front of you is because
he has another גמרא Gemara he has to accommodate. So if you
look, תוספות Tosafot says you can decide whether which is better, to
stretch the word על גבי al gabei or to deal with that
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but I'm telling you, that's what's pushing תוספות. Tosafot.
And it's not no חידוש. chiddush. It is a חידוש chiddush because
the גמרא Gemara had a whole agonizing over the issue of דרך
כרמלית. derech karmelit. דרך מקום פטור derech makom ptur might even be
more of a reason to be exempt. It's a totally new פסק.
psak.
But he stopped in your—right. No, no, no.
So, רבא's Rava חידוש chiddush is when you didn't stop, you're still
חייב chayav even though it went through מקום פטור. makom ptur. That's
a חידוש chiddush because we had to have a discussion about the
flip by a כרמלית. karmelit. The point of the משנה Mishnah is
not that you're פטור. patur. The חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah
is that it's still אסור דרבנן. asur d'rabbanan. Okay, you're right, why
the משנה Mishnah has to say you're פטור, patur, fine, it's clarifying,
but the חידוש chiddush is that it's אסור דרבנן. asur d'rabbanan. Okay,
so now continuing at the top of דף י' עמוד א', Daf
Yud Amud Aleph,
the last point of the משנה, Mishnah, which is that this ledge
is not a מקום פטור. makom ptur. This ledge can be either
רשות הרבים reshut harabim or רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, but it's talking
about a very specific case. It's talking basically that you have here
your חצר, chatzer, and you've got a ledge in front of the
חצר, chatzer, and then you have the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So
this ledge is going to say this opinion might be considered part
of the חצר, chatzer, which is a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Remember
the חצר chatzer is a courtyard surrounded by houses. So the houses
make walls and it's רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So the ledge of
the courtyard could be a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, could be part
of that, or because it opens into the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim,
it could be רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. It's not a מקום פטור.
makom ptur. So let's see what the case is here. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, or quoting the ברייתא. Baraisa. אחרים אומרים:
Acheirim omrim: אסקופה משמשת שתי רשויות. Iskofah meshameshet shtei reshuyot. This ledge
or threshold serves—that is, serving two domains. בזמן שהפתח פתוח—so Bizman shehapetach
patuach maybe it's like not an ordinary case, but a special case
like I just described to you, where it serves a רשות הרבים
reshut harabim and a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. בזמן שהפתח פתוח, Bizman
shehapetach patuach, if the door to the courtyard is open, כלפנים, kilfanin,
then it's like the inside of the courtyard, it's a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. פתח נעול. Petach naul. No, no,
well, it either means according to רש"י Rashi it means courtyard, according
to תוספות Tosafot it means courtyard or house. Okay, but whatever it
is, it's a ledge to a private domain. If the door is
open, so there's nothing interrupting the ledge and the house or the
ledge and the courtyard. It's like the inside, it's a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. פתח נעול, Petach naul, if the door is closed, so
it's just the
ledge exposed to the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, כלחוץ, kilchutz, then it
is like the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So now the גמרא Gemara
wants to understand what that case is. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואף על
גב—now V'af al gav דרישא לא לחי, d'reisha lo lechi, so the
גמרא Gemara understands
that—darn it, I keep on forgetting to bring a what do you
call it? To bring a marker, but we'll just deal with it
right now. Let's take a look. Let's assume, yeah, let's assume this
is—let's assume you've got another marker, big book. Okay, fine, yeah, that's
good. Yeah, whatever. Fine. Okay, so here you go.
You've got, you've got your—we'll assume courtyard like רש"י. Rashi. You've got
your courtyard surrounded by houses. This is the edge of the courtyard,
this is the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Now if you wanted to
carry in this courtyard, you could—three walls is not enough. You need
a לחי, lechi, you need a post here that's going to—these are
the houses? These are the houses. These are the walls of the
house. It could also be, by the way, there's—I'm not going to
worry right now about the difference between a חצר chatzer and a
מבוי, mavoi, different questions about what you need in order to allow
you to carry, whether it's two לחיים lechayin or one לחי. lechi.
Also could be that it's multiple courtyards that are opening up into
a מבוי, mavoi, into a larger alley, into a larger street. But
either way, it's fundamentally surrounded by walls. Maybe it's even a house.
And you want to carry, but in order to carry inside, if
it's only got three walls, you can't. You need a לחי, lechi,
you need a post here to let you carry. Now let's say
you have a post here that's going to let you carry.
What is the story if you want to carry—you have a pen?
Bobby, let me use your pen. Okay, this is—I'm going to use
it not to draw with. This is your post. Okay, let's—so you
can—from which point
of that post can you carry? The inner point of it inside
or the outer edge of it? Okay, so this is part of
the question about, you know, if you're at the outer edge, it's
not so obvious it's a post. If you're in the space, the
width of the post itself, right, and you're in this little strip
where the width of the post is, then it looks like a
wall, it doesn't look like a post. When you're back here, you
sort of see this post jutting out, right, but when you're here,
you understand why, like, it looks like just looks like a—looks like
a part of the wall or something, whatever. Exactly, head on. So
that’s a debate in the גמרא. Gemara. It’s a similar debate if
it’s not a post but if it’s a beam. Do you go
by the inner edge of the beam or the outer edge of
the beam? The assumption our גמרא Gemara is working with is if
it’s a beam you go by the outer edge of the beam
and you can carry under the beam. If it’s a post, you
go by the inner edge of the post and you cannot carry
in the space of the width of the post. You can only
carry behind the post. That’s the assumption. Okay. We’ll worry about it
because the beam might serve more as a wall and then you
say the edge goes down, whereas the post might be a היכר
heker and as a היכר heker it’s not as much of a
היכר heker if you’re in the width. Okay, but it’s discussed in
עירובין. Eruvin. So now the גמרא's Gemara assumption is like this: This
ledge, how can it serve as part of רשות היחיד Reshut Hayachid
if the door’s open? Right? If it- we have to assume that
it’s between- it’s not going outside of the walls, it’s some ledge
out here, it would never be part of רשות היחיד, Reshut Hayachid,
there’re no walls to it, right? So that can’t be it. It
has to be that it’s a ledge that’s still within this space.
Okay. Now, it is assuming therefore that what you’ve got is, you’ve
got- so you’ve got this space and you’ve got a door. Let's
see if the door’s open or closed. So give me a סידור
Siddur or something, that’s gonna be my door.
Thank you. Okay, so this is your door, okay? Door’s open, door’s
closed. If the door’s open, then you can- this part of the
ledge is a רשות הי- Reshut Hay- this is the ledge, let’s
call it a threshold,
right, is the- is like the outside, it’s רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim.
If the door is closed, then it’s רשות היחיד. Reshut Hayachid. Just
call it רשות היחיד, Reshut Hayachid, it’s filling it up, right? So-
so, but the point is, let's say the door’s closed- I need
another pen, I’m sorry. Thank you. The door’s closed,
it
does not fill the entire space. So you’ve got a closed door
here. With me? You’ve got a closed door, okay? And you still
have a little part here of the threshold or of the ledge
that still has these walls on it. It actually also has a
little wall of the door. The door’s serving as a wall. It’s
got the extended wall here and, okay, and maybe it’s even, you
know, it’s got this לחי, Lechi, but there’s a problem. This space
here has three walls, but it itself does not have a לחי.
Lechi. Exactly. Right. This לחי, Lechi, right, is the width of it,
but you- we said you need the back of it to help,
so it would have to be out here. All right?
But the door’s closed-
so the door’s closed here. Now, an easier way to imagine this
is even without a לחי Lechi is imagine that part of these
walls begin to extend in a little bit, you know? The- the
fourth wall starts bending in and then you have a door- a
space for the door. Okay fine, so the walls bent in, you
have space for a door, but once the door’s closed you have
this- you have the three walls but you don’t have a beginning
of a fourth wall now, something protruding in to serve as the
לחי. Lechi. Does that- pretty clear? All right, fine. So that’s the-
here give me the notepad, I’ll just draw it- just- no no,
that’s- thank you. Okay, so just
draw just to make it really- we need to start having whatever,
markers here, but anyway. Okay. So, this is even easier. Imagine it’s
like this, okay, where you don’t have a לחי, Lechi, you actually
have the beginning of a fourth wall. Yep. And then you’ve got
a door, right? You’ve got your door there, okay? So if you’ve
got that, and we’ll draw it in three dimensions, okay, when the
door is closed- so the door’s closed, so it’s like- it’s רשות
הרבים, Reshut Harabim, right? But even when the door is open, why
can you carry in that space, right? The space of the gap.
There’s no לחי. Lechi. There’s three walls, but there is no לחי.
Lechi. Exactly. Right. Why you can carry in the מבוי Mavoi is
clear because you’ve got the beginning of a fourth wall, but in
the gap you don’t have the beginning of a fourth wall, so
why does it have the status of the inside? Why can you
carry when the door is open?
All right, so
hope that was clear enough. Okay, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara.
Thank you, Bobby, for your contribution to the course. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this:
So the גמרא Gemara says ואף על גב דלית ליה לחי. Ve'af
al gav d'leit lei lechi. So you can carry in that space,
the door
space? Threshold. Not the threshold. What do you call the space that’s
in the width of the door? Does that have a name for
it?
Reveal or something?
But the- but yeah, inside of it.
Anyway, can you carry in the doorway, we’ll call it the doorway.
Can you really carry in the doorway? The doorway itself, right? Think
of it as an open door. That just makes it very easy.
You’ve got an open door, a thick door, can you carry in
the doorway? So fine, if you’re inside this room, we’ve got four
walls. But if you’re standing in the doorway, you’ve got the two
edges and the wall behind you, but you’ve only have three walls.
So wait a minute, so can you really carry in the doorway
even if the door is open?
That doesn’t have itself a לחי. Lechi. דאמר רב חמא בר גוריא
אמר רב. De'amar Rav Chama Bar Gurya Amar Rav. Says רב חמא
בר גוריא Rav Chama Bar Gurya said in the name of רב.
Rav. תוכא פתח, tocha pesach, inside the doorway itself, צריך לחי אחר
להתירו, tzarich lechi acher le-hatiro,
you need another לחי lechi outside of the doorway to allow it
to be given a fourth wall because in the doorway you only
have the two sides, the לחיים lechis or the two widths, and
the back wall. You that itself doesn't have a fourth wall. So
even if the door is open, why does it work? וכי תימא
דלית ביה ארבעה על ארבעה, vechi saima de-leis bei arba al arba,
you'll say wait, whole point here is that an איסקופא iskofa we've
been assuming now has less than four by four, that's why before
we were saying מקום פטור. makom patur. So maybe we'll say like
this, that's a very reasonable position. If the width of the doorway
is less than four by four, it itself is not a significant
space. It itself is, if you were to take it independent, it
would be a מקום פטור; makom patur; it's less than four by
four. So if it's not significant and the door's open and behind
it is a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid that you're allowed to carry
in because the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid itself has the לחי, lechi,
has the you know beginning of the fourth wall, so this just
becomes בטל battel to the רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, like it just
becomes an addendum to the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and you can
carry in it as well because it itself doesn't have any independent
significance. That makes a lot of sense. Don't judge it on its
own terms, see it as a piece of the רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid. So if you'll tell me that, that this width of the
doorway is less than four by four, so therefore even though it's
only three walls you can carry in it, דאמר רב חמא בר
גוריא אמר רב, de'amar Rav Chama bar Gurya amar Rav, תוכא פתח
tocha pesach inside the doorway, assuming the open door, אף על פי
שאין בו ארבעה על ארבעה, af al pi she-ein bo arba al
arba, even he assumes your case, even if less than four by
four and in itself it's not a significant space, צריך לחי אחר
להתירו, tzarich lechi acher le-hatiro, you want to carry in it, you
need another לחי. lechi. You cannot carry in that space unless it's
got another לחי. lechi. So how, it's yes, the inside of the
doorway is surrounded by three walls, but why can you treat it
like רשות היחיד reshus hayachid if it doesn't have the beginning of
a fourth wall, doesn't have a לחי? lechi? Now you might say
to me if it's less than four by four should be מקום
פטור;
makom
patur; I can carry anyway.
Okay so anyway, so that's a debate in the גמרא Gemara in
עירובין Eruvin about אביי ורבא, Abaye and Rava, and the basic answer
is that under certain circumstances if it's, it might just be connected
to the street that it's around it. Meaning remember מקום פטור makom
patur in a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim has to be more than
three טפחים tefachim off the ground. This isn't more than three טפחים
tefachim off the ground, whatever, under certain circumstances, yes, maybe by itself
it's a מקום פטור, makom patur, but if it's directly opening up
into a street, maybe not, or directly into a כרמלית, karmelis, maybe
not. So anyway that's more discussed in עירובין. Eruvin. But the basic
question is, I get when the door is closed, it's a problem
because it's you know, it's three walls but it doesn't have a
fourth. But even when the door is open, it's three walls and
it doesn't have a fourth. How does the door being open make
it any better? Yes Charlie.
I was just gonna ask is this a conventional doorway with a
frame and a top piece or is it more like a gate
that doesn't have it? That would make a difference.
There's no top piece. If there's a top piece that's a קורה,
korah, then you could use the top piece to serve as the
fourth wall. So yes that's a good point, there is no top
piece. Okay so now let's see the גמרא Gemara continues, okay? So
that's the question. Now I should mention by the way that even
when the door, when the door is closed, תוספות Tosafos says this
explicitly, it can't really mean that that area is a, is רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. It's surrounded, it's surrounded by three walls. So even
if we admit that it's like this thickness and the door's only
part of it, and we're talking about the space in front of
the door when the door is closed, okay but that's got... alright
fine... I got... anyway but that space is still surrounded by three
walls. So תוספות, Tosafos, okay yeah yeah, we never really mean that
when the door's closed it's רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. מדאורייתא mid'oraisa it's
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. All we mean is that you're not allowed
to carry in it. Okay now that's a bit of a stretch,
I mean if the language says when the door's closed it's part
of the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, it makes it sound like you
wouldn't be doing a מלאכה melacha carrying from the רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim into it. But both רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos pretty much
agree how to read this גמרא. Gemara. There might be other ways,
but they say when the door's closed it just means you're not
allowed to carry in it. It does not mean it's a רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. Biblically it's רשות היחיד; reshus hayachid; it's three walls.
But the question is, but what about when the door's open? That's
true. Because even though you've got a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid here,
but in this space there's no, there's no fourth wall. And even
though it's connected to רשות היחיד reshus hayachid with a fourth wall,
and even if the door's open, why would we let you carry
it if within that space itself there's no beginning of a fourth
wall? Okay so that is the question. So let's see the גמרא's
Gemara answer to this. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, הכא באיסקופת מבוי
עסקינן. hacha be-iskofas mavoi askinan. We're talking about an, about the threshold
of a מבוי. mavoi. So תוספות Tosafos says that sounds like until
now we've been talking about a house or a חצר, chatzer, not
a מבוי. mavoi. For us it's really immaterial, we'll just note that.
Fine. So we're talking about the איסקופא iskofa of some type of
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Now, but here's why we're gonna, how
we're gonna answer your question. חציו מקורה וחציו שאינו מקורה. chetzyo mekureh
ve-chetzyo she-eino mekureh. It does have a partial roof on top of
this doorway. וקירויו כלפי פנים. ve-kiroyav kelapei pnim.
But the part that has the roof, the beam, is towards
the inside.
פתח פתוח כלפנים פתח נעול כלחוץ. pesach patuach kelifnim, pesach na'ul kelachutz.
Wait one
minute.
Okay. The case is like this: here is your, well, we'll use
this, it might even be easier. Okay, whoops. These are my wall,
three walls, these are the beginning of my fourth wall. So again,
inside here, I've got three walls and even beginnings of fourth walls,
I'm totally okay. How about inside the doorway width? That's been our
issue. Inside the doorway width, you only have three walls, right? That's
been our issue. So comes the answer and he says what we're
dealing with is that you've got half of it has a roof
on top. Now, I'll tell you in a minute, it doesn't even
really have to be half, but the key has to be that
this, this roof, this beam, is less than four טפחים tefachim wide.
Okay? So if the door is closed, okay, and the door is
right here at the back of the width, it doesn't really fill
the width. Okay. So if the door is closed, then the space
over here, okay, it's got a beam over part of it, but
you've still got a problem. It's only got three walls. Why does
the beam not help? The beam doesn't help because because a beam
that is over a space less than four טפחים tefachim does not
serve as a beam for the הלכה halacha purposes of being able
to count as a fourth wall. So if the door is closed,
you've still got three walls and a little bit of a beam
on top of here, but you still don't have an acceptable thing
that counts to help you for your fourth wall. And fill the
whole thing? Well, it's really not רש״י Rashi says about filling the
whole thing. It's really about being four טפחים. tefachim. If the beam
were four טפחים, tefachim, then yes, then it would work. You have
three walls and a beam of four טפחים tefachim and you would
be fine. Okay?
And in a minute, that would never be a רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid,
would it?
I'm sorry?
It says צריך לחי אחר להתירו, tzarich lechi acher lehatiro, but how
would that help if it's less than four טפחים?
tefachim? Wait a minute, let me just finish the case and then
you'll ask your question. Okay. So that would be, that's when the
door is closed. Now let me just once check one second רש״י.
Rashi.
One minute.
Just one second, hold on. Ah,
so okay, yes. So the key here is it's not, I'm sorry,
the key is not that the beam per se is less than
four. A normal case of a if I had a normal courtyard,
right, let's say this itself was my courtyard, I could have a
very thin beam and that would be fine. The beam itself does
not have to have the width of four. The key is is
that the beam, to be meaningful, has to be over, relating to
a space that is at least four by four. As we've said
that a space less than four by four is not a meaningful
space. So here's the difference. If the beam itself was at the
edge of a four by four space, right, and then so you
closed your door but this was a four by four space and
you had your beam, you'd be okay: one, two, three walls and
a beam that related to a space of four by four. But
if the beam is towards the back and therefore the space under
it is less than four by four with the door closed, it
does no good. A beam does no good to a space less
than four by four. But if you open your doorway, so now
the space that relates to the beam is the whole courtyard, right?
And in that case, you can, the beam does work and you
can carry in the space behind from the beam backwards. Okay. So
again, it's a obviously it's here, we'll do this, this is a
better beam. Okay. Here's the case: this is your threshold, your אסקופה.
eskupa. If the doorway is open, then
fine, your רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, your allowed space doesn't end here
where your לחי lechi is, it goes all the way up to
where your beam is, right? That's what we said, and by the
outer edge of the beam. So when you've got your beam over
here, if you didn't have your beam, you could carry until it
started going in, which is your לחי. lechi. Because your beam, you
can go all the way up to the outer edge of the
beam. That's when the door is open. But as soon as the
door is closed and you have to look at this space by
itself, since it's less than four by four, the beam does no
good and you cannot carry in this space even behind the beam.
Okay.
So that's the example the גמרא Gemara
gives.
Less than four by four is מקום פטור, makom patur, I'm
more strict.
Once yeah, that's a good point if it's מקום פטור, makom patur,
but for some reason this less than four by four winds up
being a כרמלית karmelis and not a מקום פטור, makom patur, and
that's discussed in the what do you call it's discussed in עירובין,
Eruvin, basically ask that question. But it's a very good point.
But don't put us off and
say it was discussed in שבת. Shabbos. Right. Okay, when we get
to it in עירובין, Eruvin, I would promise you we will discuss
it. All right. Now it's actually interesting, it's discussed at exactly the
parallel דף, daf, like when on דף ו׳ daf vav here in
שבת Shabbos when we were discussing the definition of רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim and רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, there's an almost directly parallel discussion
on דף ו׳ daf vav in עירובין Eruvin and here on דף
ט׳ daf tes where it's discussing the threshold and whether the space
four by four, it's discussed on דף ט׳ daf tes in עירובין.
Eruvin. So anyway, just another proof of תורה מסיני. Torah MiSinai. Okay.
Now. Okay, so that's his answer. So his answer is so again
the question is why when the door is open does it work,
it's only three walls you don't have a לחי lechi or a
קורה korah in that space. And the answer now is you do
have a קורה korah in that space and therefore when the door
is open you can use it up to the קורה korah but
when the door is closed if it's a small space the קורה
korah doesn't work. And Michael's question about isn't four by four more
lenient? That gets discussed. But I should say by the way here
the whole space could be more than four by four, it's just
the space up to the קורה korah is less and therefore the
קורה korah does not work. That's one answer. Okay, one more answer.
רב אשי... Rav Ashi...
okay, רב אשי אמר לעולם בסקופת בית עסקינן. Rav Ashi amar le'olam
b'eskupas bayis askinan. We're talking about what we maybe were talking about
earlier about the threshold or the ledge of a house, וכגון u'kegon
meaning why it matters house or מבוי mavoi or חצר... chatzer... מבוי
mavoi whatever is not our issue. תוספות Tosafos deals with it about
whether you need two לחיים lechayim or whatever, that's not really what
we're going to focus on. Anyway here's the key of the difference:
וכגון שקירה בשתי קורות שאין בזו ארבעה ואין בזו ארבעה ואין בין
זו לזו שלשה והדלת באמצע. u'kegon shekira b'shtei koros she'ein be'zu arba'ah
ve'ein be'zu arba'ah ve'ein bein zu le'zu sheloshah ve'hadeles b'emtza. Okay, so
what you've got here is you have two, I need another pen,
Bobby, give me your other pen. Okay, you've got, no just one
more. Okay, you've got two, two beams. Okay, now neither beam is
four טפחים tepachim wide, but they're with—but each beam is let's say
a טפח, tefach, but they're within three טפחים tepachim of one another.
So therefore if they can be allowed to do their job, just
let me do my... right, then they combine with לבוד lavud and
they become like four טפחים. tepachim. Okay, if—but the thing is—how much
is the whole space here? The whole space here is four טפחים.
tepachim. Okay, so if you let them do their work...
in your case it's you said one one and two?
No, let's say one one and two and a half, four and
a half טפחים. tepachim. So if you let them operate, right, they
combine and then they are—they would be four טפחים tepachim and whatever
and the space would be four טפחים tepachim and you could do
stuff under it and שלום על ישראל. shalom al Yisrael. Okay, but
that's because of לבוד, lavud, okay and then whatever and then that
would work. But there's a door, the door goes right in between
them. Okay? So if the door is closed, you cannot—they cannot operate
together. Okay, the door is seen to separate their function. So then
if you're on the outside of the door, you're back to the
same problem. You have a space less than four by four, okay,
and you have three walls but you don't have something helping for
the fourth wall. Now if the door is open however, okay then
the whole thing becomes one unit four by four whatever and you
can go up to the outer edge. Now again somebody would ask
me why—why do you need it to be four טפחים? tepachim? You
just said that it could be only a טפח, tefach, who even
needs it to be together? But the basic point that רש״י Rashi
makes is that even if the space it's serving is less than
four טפחים, tepachim, it would work if the קורה korah itself were
four טפחים. tepachim. So if—so if it were not for the door
interrupting the fact that these could combine to be four טפחים tepachim
would allow you to operate under the space even if the space
under it would be less than that. But the door stops them
from working together. Okay, it's a variation of the same answer which
is basically the space you have when the door's open has a
functioning קורה. korah. Because then it's a space bigger than four טפחים
tepachim or then the קורה korah magically becomes bigger than four טפחים.
tepachim. When the door is closed it stops being a functioning קורה.
korah. Either because the space is less than four טפחים tepachim or
because the קורה korah itself by being divided by the door and
being two halves stops being considered four טפחים. tepachim. You see the
difference? I don't know, because it's taking into consideration other issues that
we're not getting into about the difference between מבוי mavoi and בית
bayis and so on. Okay. So that's his answer.
Okay. פתח פתוח כפנים פתח נעול כלחוץ. Pesach pasuach k'fanim pesach na'ul
k'lachutz. So that was the end of that quite dense discussion and
we really need the markers but I think you got the idea.
And when we get back to עירובין Eruvin exactly this same דף
daf five years from now, five years five months from
now, then you can bother me more about this. Okay let's take
a look.
Let me just see one more thing before I just wrap this
up. Hold on.
Let me just double check רש״י. Rashi.
All right, so just to clarify again why we said two separate
things. רש״י Rashi said if this were—here it is right before—if this
were—if the entire קורה korah was a whole four טפחים tepachim and
you had the door in the middle and you couldn't divide it
up into two. that even though the space outside of the door
was less than four טפחים, tefachim, by virtue of being covered by
a קורה kora that itself was bigger, was was four טפחים, tefachim,
right, even if part of it was behind, this is four טפחים
tefachim and this is your door, so even though this space here
is less than four טפחים tefachim and we said a קורה kora
doesn't work in a space less than four טפחים, tefachim, here it
would work because the whole קורה kora is four טפחים. tefachim. Okay,
but then the door could even be closed, it can be open,
it's all underneath it, three walls and a קורה, kora, even though
the space is less, it would work because the קורה kora itself
was four. So that's why he says this example to make it
interesting is that the קורה kora is four in a certain way
if you use לבוד. lavud. If it were a real four you
could carry in the space even with the door closed. But since
it's only four by virtue of לבוד, lavud, the door stops it
from being four, separates the two, and therefore the space underneath is
neither four by four, I mean in front of the door is
neither four by four nor is it covered by a קורה kora
that is four טפחים, tefachim, because that is divided by the door.
And therefore you can't carry. But had it been a solid קורה,
kora, even with the door in the middle, you would be allowed
to carry. So that's just to make it clear why he gave
the more complicated case of being a separated קורה, kora, two קורות.
korot. Yes. All right, question? No.
You see it like with a house, like that because the roof
is more than four טפחים tefachim and if the outside of the
door then it would be less than four טפחים, tefachim, so therefore
you'd be okay if the roof, if the edge of the roof
extended over. Exactly, exactly. And that would be a good practical example,
you know, if you had a roof that sort of hung over,
right there, your door, you got
a little roof.
Yeah, exactly. So even if that space is less than four by
four, right, okay. All right, so let's now wrap this up so
we can get to a brand new topic. Yay. והא דתנן איסקופה
גבוה עשרה ורחבה ארבעה הרי זו רשות לעצמה. Ve-ha de-tenan iskopa gevoha
asara ve-rechava arba'a arei zu reshuta le-atzma. So if the, however, the
threshold is in front of your courtyard is four wide and ten
high, then it is its own domain, its רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid,
it's four by four and ten high. But it's not just saying
its רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, it seems to be saying something else,
it's a רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid but a distinct רשות היחיד reshus
ha-yachid from the courtyard. So the גמרא Gemara says what did that
mean to say? מסייע ליה לרבי יצחק בר אבדימי. Mesaye lei le-Rabbi
Yitzchak bar Avdimi. Support for Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi, דאמר רבי יצחק
בר אבדימי אמר רבי אומר היה רבי מאיר. De-amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar
Avdimi amar Rabbi omer haya Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir used to say,
who is אחרים acherim in our משנה? mishna? By the way, our
משנה mishna is אחרים. acherim. We'll learn this is אחרים, acherim, so
this is Rabbi Meir. כל מקום שאתה מוצא שני רשויות והן רשות
אחת. Kol makom she-ata motzei shenei reshuyos ve-hein reshuta achas. If you
have two places which are structurally separate spaces, even if they're both
רשויות היחיד. reshuyos ha-yachid. So you have a רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid
next to another רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, but it's clearly a distinct
רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, not based on ownership, but based on structurally.
Let's say for example like a courtyard surrounded by hedges in your
house?
Maybe. One example would be let's say you've got a rooftop and
the courtyard below. Very, you know, clearly one's high, one's low, okay,
or maybe you have, I don't know, separate rooftops or something like
that, maybe separate houses. Okay, so they're structurally different רשויות היחיד, reshuyos
ha-yachid, but they're all have the הלכה halacha of רשות היחיד. reshus
ha-yachid. Can you carry from one to the next? Very important question.
Can you carry from רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid to רשות היחיד? reshus
ha-yachid? So he says כגון עמוד ברשות היחיד גבוה עשרה ורחב ארבעה.
Kegon amud bi-reshus ha-yachid gevoha asara ve-rachav arba'a.
So he says case where clearly they're like different heights, they're not
just a wall between them or whatever. In the middle of your
רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid here, in the middle of here we've got,
I don't know, a filing cabinet, ten טפחים tefachim high, four by
four, okay? Right here in the middle of my house. Can I
put something on the top of the filing cabinet? I hope so.
Right? I hope so. Every day we take our books off the
filing cabinet. So he said אסור לכתף עליו. Assur le-katef alav.
You're not allowed to put stuff on top of that. Why? גזירה
משום כתף רשות הרבים. Gezeira mishum ketef reshus ha-rabim. If I start
putting stuff on top of a filing cabinet in my house, I'm
going to put it on top of a similar filing cabinet or
a similar structure out in the רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim. And in
the רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim
it's a רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, so then I would be carrying
from רשות reshus to רשות היחיד. reshus ha-yachid. So my sense is,
why? So I don't think, psychologically I don't think it's a bad
concern. Right? It doesn't feel like carrying, it feels like you're just
putting something on top of a filing cabinet. So if I could
do it indoors, why can't I do it outdoors? I'm not taking
to a separate domain, I'm just putting it on top of a,
on top of an object. So he says we don't let you
do it indoors, you might come to do it outdoors. Now תוספות
Tosafot says how far do you take this? Can I not carry
something from my ground floor to my second floor? Because you know
it's one רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid to another רשות היחיד. reshus ha-yachid.
So תוספות Tosafot tries to say well this is particularly a case
where it doesn't really have obvious separate walls, it feels like just
an object standing in the middle of your רשות. reshus. If it
actually had its own walls like your upstairs has its own walls
from your downstairs, I mean they're the same walls on the outside
but you know you're surrounded by walls, then you obviously know you're
in a רשות היחיד. reshus ha-yachid. So to take it from like
my house and if we have a window between our houses and
stick it into your house, that would be fine. Okay, but taking
it from let's say my my... my courtyard which is surrounded by
walls and putting it on the top of like a rooftop or
putting it on the top of a doghouse that's a high doghouse
or something that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would be אסור
assur because then it doesn't feel it feels like you're not putting
it it doesn't feel like you're putting it in a רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid. It just feels like you're putting it on some type
of a on top of a structure and you'll come to do
it in a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Thankfully we do not פסקן
pasken like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir so you don't have to worry
about it but that is explaining what this position is.
You're saying it's not a problem if it's in your house because
the whole thing is...
no it is a problem if it's in your house because the
bookcase is not surrounded by... it's surrounded by its own walls but
what makes the bookcase its own רשות היחיד reshus hayachid is not
obvious. The walls of the bookcase are not obvious and that's why
it's a problem.
Okay so when wasn't it a problem according to him?
If you go from your downstairs to your upstairs because what makes
your upstairs a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid are the walls around your
upstairs and you see those walls. What makes your neighbor's house a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid are his walls and you see those walls
but you don't you're not obviously aware of the idea that your
bookcase has walls or that the filing cabinet has walls. Okay but
anyway we don't פסקן pasken like him. Now we move on to
a totally new topic. Let's take a look. Radical shift. Okay. So
we start with a whole משנה mishna which is about carrying. Maybe
it's somewhat of an introduction to the fact that the משנה mishna
not this משנה mishna but the משנה mishna after this one the
third משנה mishna is going to talk about not going out ערב
שבת erev Shabbos with your certain things in your pocket because you'll
forget they're in your pocket and you'll wind up carrying on שבת.
Shabbos. So leading into that is a משנה mishna here about not
doing stuff you'll come to forget. So we have one משנה mishna
telling you about carrying. משנה Mishna number two tells you don't do
things before a particular time you'll come to forget and then the
combination of them are going to lead to משנה mishna three which
is going to say don't be carrying stuff in your pocket ערב
שבת erev Shabbos you'll come to forget and you'll come to carry
on שבת. Shabbos. So now we're talking about coming to forget. Let's
take a look at this משנה mishna top of ט עמוד ב.
tes amud beis. לא ישב אדם לפני הספר lo yeishev adam lifnei
hasapar a person cannot sit in front of a barber סמוך למנחה
samuch lamincha near מנחה mincha time עד שיפלל ad sheyispalel until he
davens because having nothing to do with שבת Shabbos but doing things
that we'll talk about that are going to take time and you'll
come to forget. ולא יכנס אדם למרחץ velo yichanes adam lemerchatz don't
go into a
bathhouse ולא לבורסקי velo le-burski or to a tannery who's working some
leathers that you've given him to process. ולא לאכול velo leechol and
don't go start sitting down to eat ולא לדין velo ladin or
go sitting down to be part of a court case presumably you're
the judge maybe it applies to the litigants as well. Don't do
begin any of these processes that could start take time when it's
already getting close to the time of davening. Okay because then you'll
get absorbed in them and you'll forget to daven. ואם התחיל veim
hitchil but if you did begin presumably even if you began when
you shouldn't have begun at the time we told you not to
even if if you did begin אין מפסיקין ein mafsikin we let
you continue we don't tell you you don't have to interrupt. We
let you finish. Now another גמרא Gemara says clearly that's only assuming
that you there'll be time after you're done. So we don't make
you interrupt we can say okay we'll trust you to do it
after you're done. But if you're going to miss the opportunity to
daven until you're done with your meal or your haircut then you
have to stop and daven and that would override. But if but
we're right but it's not going to
override but but assuming you will have time we will trust you
to take care of it after once you're already in the middle.
מפסיקין לקריאת שמע ואין מפסיקין לתפילה mafsikin likrias shema ve-ein mafsikin litefilla
and there's another difference as well. That's only we're talking about davening.
Davening is rabbinic. So therefore you already started again what's not said
here but said elsewhere is you will hopefully presumably have time afterwards
and anyway we're dealing with a rabbinic issue. In that case we're
not going to tell you you have to interrupt the thing you're
in the middle of. But if you won't have time to finish
it not said here but said elsewhere then you have to interrupt.
Or even if you will have time but if it's a biblical
issue like saying שמע shema then we're extra anxious and then we
actually will tell you to interrupt even once you got started. Yeah
Ari? קריאת
שמע krias shema for מנחה? mincha? No it's a different scenario meaning
not you're right not the same scenario. It's morning or it's evening
right a different scenario not the same scenario.
I was going to ask why are they worried about saying the
שמע shema shortly before שבת Shabbos starts because this isn't
שבת Shabbos this has nothing to do with שבת Shabbos this is
Wednesday okay?
Like I said you have one משנה mishna that tells you carrying
one משנה mishna that tells you a general anxiety we have about
doing things that you'll forget about okay on Wednesday and then we're
going to have a third משנה mishna that says not doing certain
things Friday afternoon because because you'll come to carry basically a combination
of the themes of משנה mishna one and two. Let's take a
look at the
גמרא. Gemara. הי סמוך למנחה hi samuch lamincha which מנחה mincha are
you right before? Now there the way we divide the time is
מנחה גדולה mincha gedola means the big מנחה mincha time because it's
a big time it's five and a half hours it's from 12:30
to 6:00 I'm assuming a perfect day sunrise at 6:00 sunset at
6:00 so מנחה גדולה mincha gedola is from 12:30 to 6:00. just
convert it for seasonal hours and seasonal sunrise and sunset. We can
start saying מנחה mincha at seasonal 12:30. Why? Because that's when it
becomes the afternoon. There's actually two interesting רש"י'ס Rashis about why not
12:01. One is technically it is 12:01, but people it's hard without
watches, it's hard to tell the precise time, so we give ourselves
a buffer zone and we say 12:30. There's another רש"י, Rashi, other
רש"י'ס Rashis and one here that says, no, 12 up till 12:30
it's not yet the afternoon. Meaning fine on paper it is, but
experientially the sun is still directly overhead. Within the period between 11:30
and 12:30, the half hour before and after, right, it's really midday.
The sun experiences as directly overhead. You only start experiencing the sun
as beginning to set from 12:30 on. Okay, so even though technically
it's past the midpoint, you don't experience it as beginning to set
until after 12:30. So anyway, that's a different explanation. Either way, afternoon
for דאוונען davenning מנחה mincha and for bringing the קרבן תמיד Korban
Tamid is 12:30 on. From that time on you can say מנחה.
mincha. However, that's not usually they would not bring the מנחה mincha
that early. Usually they would bring it more around תמיד tamid that
early. Usually they would bring it around 3:30 in the afternoon, usually
not later than 3:30. So that from 3:30 till six is considered
to be מנחה קטנה, Mincha Ketana, the smaller מנחה, mincha, and that
actually is the ideal time to דאווען daven מנחה. mincha. It's a
little funny. Why didn't you say the ideal time was not later
than 3:30 since that's when they would bring it, but we won't
worry about that right now. So which time period do we say
don't start doing any of these things before מנחה? mincha? Does it
mean before 12:30? Then I've got five and a half hours left
in the day. I can't begin this stuff? Or does it mean
no, starting at 3:30 on when I only have two and a
half hours left in the day? Obviously. A lot more time, I
know, but you know, you get involved and then you forget. It's
not like it's in the forefront of your memory. After you go
to your barber, you say, oh yeah, I gotta go pick up
those groceries and dah dah dah, you know, whatever, you get involved.
So anyway, that's the issue. Logically, you'd assume מנחה קטנה. Mincha Ketana.
מנחה גדולה Mincha Gedola is much too much time to be concerned
about. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Any other question?
No.
Let's not,
that's not שמע. Shema. That's going to be, yeah,
we're back, the main theme of the משנה Mishnah is מנחה. mincha.
It was just a footnote at the end of the משנה. Mishnah.
That if it's שמע, Shema, you have to interrupt.
But he says if it's, if it's we don't have to interrupt.
Ah, but you're not allowed to start. But you're not allowed to
start. Okay, so we're going the main theme here, the משנה, Mishnah,
right, wait, if it's already started don't interrupt, but the משנה Mishnah
starts by saying don't start. So when is it you're not supposed
to start? Which מנחה mincha are you in? So let's take a
look. So אילימא למנחה גדולה, eileima leMincha Gedola, the מנחה גדולה, Mincha
Gedola, אמאי לא? amai lo? Why not start? האיכא שהות היום טובא?
Haika she'os hayom tuba? You have a lot of time in the
day, you have five and a half hours, big deal, go get
your haircut. אלא סמוך למנחה קטנה. Ela samuch leMincha Ketana. So you'll
say it means that you're right before מנחה קטנה. Mincha Ketana. So
also, by the way, he maybe even not at מנחה קטנה, Mincha
Ketana, maybe right before, a half hour before. So let's say it's
about
at 3:00, don't start these things, it's right before מנחה קטנה, Mincha
Ketana, don't get started. So one minute, אם התחילו אין מפסיקין. im
hitchilu ein mafsikin. Let's go to the next part of the משנה.
Mishnah. Once you started, you don't have to stop.
נימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי יהושע בן לוי? Neima tehevei tiyuvta deRabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi? That could be a contradiction of רבי יהושע בן לוי.
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Why? דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, De'amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, he said, כיון שהגיע זמן תפלת המנחה, keivan shehigia
zman tefilas haMincha, once the time of מנחה mincha came, אסור לאדם
שיטעום כלום קודם שיתפלל. assur la'adam sheyitam klum kodem sheyispalel. It's forbidden
for a person to taste anything before you דאווען. daven. Now, it's
not exactly clear how this contradicts רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, that's also what our משנה Mishnah said: don't start eating.
It doesn't tell you maybe when you start you're, maybe if you
start you're allowed to continue. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that the
phrasing אסור לטעום כלום assur litom klum is very absolute. And what
that means is even if you started eating, it's אסור. assur. It
remains אסור assur even if you started. So the גמרא Gemara says,
well, how do you fit the idea that it remains אסור assur
even if you started with our משנה Mishnah that says if you
started you don't have to interrupt? So it says we can understand
it if one is talking about מנחה גדולה Mincha Gedola and one
is talking about מנחה קטנה. Mincha Ketana. If you started at מנחה
גדולה, Mincha Gedola, don't interrupt. If you started at מנחה קטנה, Mincha
Ketana, then stop eating. That we can reconcile. But if they're both
talking about מנחה קטנה, Mincha Ketana, we can't really reconcile those two
statements. So that's pushing the גמרא Gemara to say that the don't
start but if you started don't stop begins all the way at
מנחה גדולה. Mincha Gedola. Okay, and this harsh statement of אסור assur
is only מנחה קטנה. Mincha Ketana. Well, let's just read a little
more. So but if it starts at מנחה גדולה, Mincha Gedola, why
is that a concern? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
תפילת מנחה. Tefilas Mincha. לעולם סמוך למנחה גדולה. Le'olam samuch leMincha Gedola.
No, you're right, his statement don't eat anything is starting at מנחה
קטנה, Mincha Ketana, even if, even if you started, stop. When we
say don't begin, that's מנחה גדולה. Mincha Gedola. So why is it
an issue? You got five and a half hours. ובתספורת בן אלעשה
Uvesisporet ben elasha or because we're talking about a very fancy haircut.
There's this guy בן אלעשה Ben Elasha spent a lot of time.
money to learn this very how to do this very fancy hairdo
that every single thread of hair the end starts touch the beginning
of the of the root of the next hair, you know, you
can go in and for these type of hairdos, right, what do
they call where they do the whole things with the beads and
whatever? Do you know what I'm talking about?
Anyway, not just braiding. You can do a type of a hair
thing that takes six hours, okay? That's what we're talking about. We're
talking about a special hair thing that takes six hours and that's
why you can't start it even at מנחה גדולה mincha gedola, *Mincha
Gedola*. Okay. ולא למרחץ *V'lo l'merchatz*, so what does it mean don't
go into a bathhouse? לכולה מירסא דמרחץ *L'cula mirsa d'merchatz*. We're talking
you're not just taking a bath, but you're doing the whole spa.
First you're doing a שוויץ *shvitz* and then you're doing a this
and then you're doing a that. You're talking about a whole spa,
you got the whole afternoon in front of you. ולא לבורסקי *V'lo
l'burski*, not for the tanner, לבורסקי גדולה *l'burski gedola*, to the whole
big of the big tanning process, the whole process from the beginning
till the end. We're going to, you know, you're doing the whatever,
something that can take hours. ולא לאכול *V'lo l'echol*, not to eat,
בסעודה גדולה *b'seuda gedola*, a big meal. What's a big meal? Right,
so תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says like a wedding meal. Okay, so something
that's like you got it's got a couple hours you're going to
be here for. Okay, so those ולא לדין *v'lo l'din* or to
a case of a court, בתחילת דין *b'techilat din* when you're starting
the court case. Then it could run out for hours, for days.
Okay, so now saying it this way, it says fine, we're talking
about about 12:30. But the only things you can't start are huge
deals. So that actually leads to a lenient ruling which would say
that any normal type of activity you can begin at least at
the מנחה גדולה mincha gedola *Mincha Gedola*. Maybe not the מנחה קטנה
mincha ketana *Mincha Ketana*. Maybe the מנחה קטנה mincha ketana *Mincha Ketana*
time you even if you began you'd have to stop, that phrase
of אסור asur לטעום כלום *assur lit'om klum*, but at least the
מנחה Mincha. גדולה *Mincha Gedola* time is only an issue when it's
a huge deal. That's answer number one. רב אחא בר יעקב אמר
*Rav Achai bar Yaakov amar*, רב אחא בר יעקב *Rav Achai bar
Yaakov* says, לעולם בתספורת דידן *le'olam b'tisporet didan*, a normal haircut, and
even so you can't do it starting at 12:30. לכתחילה מאי לא
*L'chatchila mai lo*, so why not start a haircut at 12:30? גזירה
שמא ישבר הזוג *Gzeira shema yishaver ha-zog*, we're afraid that the scissors
will break and it wasn't a trivial thing to get another scissors.
Then you have to go and you have to, I don't know,
go to the metal guy and gotta go sharpen it and whatever.
Right. Okay. ולא למרחץ *V'lo l'merchatz*, not to the מרחץ *merchatz*, לאזיאמא
*l'azyama*, just for שוויץ *shvitz*. So לכתחילה מאי לא *l'chatchila mai lo*,
so why not? That's not, that's only an hour, whatever it is.
גזירה שמא יתעלפה *Gzeira shema yitalfe*. No, we're afraid that you might
faint during the שוויצן *shvitzing* and then you'll run to the emergency
room and that'll be a couple of hours. So you're right, normal
circumstances it wouldn't be a problem, but who knows what can happen.
ולא לבורסקי *V'lo l'burski*, the tanner, לעיוני בעלמא *l'iyuni be'alma*, just you're
just going there to check up on how is everything going. Just
doing a quick checking on on the hides and then you're going
to go home. So why not?
These are your hides.
You, your hides and you might be the tanner, whatever, it's not
exactly clear here. Why? לכתחילה מאי לא *L'chatchila mai lo*, so why
not? דילמא חזי פסידא בזביני *Dilma chazi pseida b'zvini* because then you're
just checking until you find a problem, but if something is wrong
then ומטריד *u-mitrid* you'll get very preoccupied by it and then you'll
have to spend hours there. ולא לאכול *V'lo l'echol*, not to eat,
בסעודה קטנה *b'seuda ketana*, even a small meal. לכתחילה מאי לא *L'chatchila
mai lo*, why not? If it's five and a half hours? דילמא
אתי לאמשוכי *Dilma ati l'amshuchei*, cause you know, small meals have ways
of becoming big meals, so even if you're only intending a small
meal, you don't. Okay. ולא לדין *V'lo l'din*, not for a judgment,
even בגמר דין *b'gmar din*, even if you're just wrapping things up.
לכתחילה מאי לא *L'chatchila mai lo*, so why can't you begin it
even at the beginning of five and a half hours at 12:30?
דילמא חזי טעמא לסתור הדין *Dilma chazi ta'ama l'stur ha-din*, maybe you
like this sounds like it's assuming you're the judge, but you can
reverse it for you the litigant. Anyway, maybe they'll see a reason.
They came in just to wrap up. Okay, we heard all the
arguments, we just have an hour left to record everything, summarize and
wrap up. Then in the middle of summarizing somebody raises an objection
and then you have to revisit the whole case. So all these
cases, you're right, you can't begin even a small thing starting at
12:30, starting at מנחה Mincha. גדולה *Mincha Gedola*, because who knows where
it will lead. Now that's very מחמיר machmir *machmir*, right? That would
basically mean that there's what we can't do any activity starting at
starting at 12:30? Forget דאוונען *davening*. So on Wednesday you can't do
anything at 12:30 because who knows how long it's going to take?
And מנחה Mincha *Mincha*? What? What? You can't even דאוון daven *daven*
מנחה Mincha. *Mincha*? But everybody would have to דאוון daven *daven* מנחה
Mincha *Mincha* at 12:30, okay, we can't דאוון daven *daven* a late
מנחה Mincha? *Mincha*. So how do we פסקן *posken* about this? So
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* first of all says, well first of all we
פסקן *posken* the first position. Now why do we פסקן *posken* the
first position? That says only big activities you can't start at 12:30.
So it's an interesting point here about about the סתם stam *stam*
of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. If you look at the תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot* בתספורת שבן אלעשה *b'tisporet she-ben Alasha*, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says like
this, he says
he
says והלכתא *v'hilchata* the last of narrow lines of תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*,
you know, he says והלכתא כוותיה *v'hilchata kvatei*,
the position that only huge activities you can't begin לגבי רב אחא
בר יעקב *legabei Rav Achai bar Yaakov*. You see where? You see
the word בתספורת *b'tisporet* right before the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* lines start
getting wide. We rule like the first position against רב אחא בר
יעקב *Rav Achai bar Yaakov*, the second that says even small activities
no. Why? דאמורא קמא
*d'amora kama* I'm sorry, I'm sorry, start... two lines higher than that.
He says like this, three lines higher than that. He says like
this: the הלכה כלישנא קמא three lines before it gets wide, we
rule like the first approach דסתם לן הש"ס desatam lan HaShas because
the first approach was said in the anonymous voice of the Gemara,
was an unnamed position. For רב אשי שבתרא סידר את הש"ס, Rav
Ashi she-basra seder et ha-Shas,
the anonymous portion of the Gemara was written by רב אשי. Rav
Ashi. Some academics now disagree, think it was after רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, תוספות Tosafos ascribes it to רב אשי. Rav Ashi. So he
is the anonymous voice of the Gemara. והלכתא כוותיה לגבי רב אחא
בר יעקב v'hilchasa k'vosei legabei Rav Achah bar Yaakov and we rule
like רב אשי Rav Ashi who is later against an earlier position
because הלכה כבתראי, halacha k'basrai, we go like a later position. So
תוספות first of all would be completely unliveable to do like the
second opinion. תוספות says we rule like the first opinion, only big
activities you can't begin. But the reason he argues is because we
rule like the סתם stam of the Gemara over an unnamed position.
The סתם stam is רב אשי, Rav Ashi, the סתם is בתראי.
basrai. Now how does the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch actually rule? Interestingly
the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch actually rules the most מחמיר machmir like
the second opinion. The שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says starting at 12:30
you can't do even these small activities they might become big activities.
You've got to daven before you even sit down to eat a
small meal or anything. Maybe you can munch on an apple but
don't even have a sandwich starting at 12:30, even a small meal.
Comes along the רמ"א Rema and the רמ"א Rema has a whole
range of positions. The רמ"א Rema first of all says like תוספות
that no, only big meals are אסור asur starting at 12:30, but
at מנחה קטנה mincha ketana. you can't begin even a small meal.
Okay, that he does say. Maybe if you began a small meal
remember what the Gemara sounded like that if you began at מנחה
קטנה mincha ketana you have to interrupt. Okay, the רמ"א Rema doesn't
even mention that. That's one opinion. One opinion says that the issue
is don't begin a big meal, you know, whatever. Then he gives
other opinions. He says look, maybe a big meal you can't begin
even at מנחה Mincha, גדולה, but a small meal you can begin
anytime even at מנחה קטנה. mincha ketana. So the only thing ever
אסור asur is a big meal. Small things you can begin the
whole day which doesn't sound like it in the Gemara, but okay.
Then he has another approach, it says maybe nothing you can begin
at מנחה Mincha, קטנה even a small thing, but מנחה Mincha גדולה
you can begin anything even a big meal. So he's got one
approach which says it's all about something big, never begin something big
even early. Another approach which says but anything small is always okay.
Another approach that says it's all about the later time, don't begin
anything at the later time even small but the earlier time you
can begin everything. And what he says at the end is נהגו
nahagu to take both leniencies. So that the only thing that is
אסור is a big meal at מנחה Mincha קטנה. Okay? Anything at
an early time even big is okay, so you're invited to an
afternoon wedding that starts at 1:00, go you can sit down to
the wedding meal before davening מנחה.
Anything small is okay even late. The only thing you can't begin
is something big at the late time. So the only problem is
don't sit down to a wedding meal at 3:30 before you've davened
מנחה. They usually daven מנחה anyway after the chassan's tish. This is
what the רמ"א Rema rules. Now it doesn't fit well in the
Gemara so he says here then he says it seems to me
the reason we're מקיל mekil is because we usually have people to
remind us what time davening is. People go around announcing what time
davening is and therefore we can be more lenient that we won't
come to forget. And we use that a lot as a leniency.
Especially if you regularly go to a davening at a certain time
so that and you know naturally you know that time and you
have your watch especially nowadays you can set little alarms on your
watch, you can ask somebody to remind us. So that's ways of
dealing with this of saying if you have reminders it might make
it different. But just to be aware that the רמ"א Rema's ruling
is much more lenient than we would have expected from the Gemara.
So there's one question within the Gemara do we take the strict
or lenient approach? But the רמ"א Rema winds up saying the only
thing we wind up being מחמיר for is a huge deal late
in the day. Okay so let's just now wrap up the discussion
in the Gemara about this.
Gemara says like
this: okay, מאימתי התחלת תספורת? me'eimasai hat-chalas tispores? Now whenever we said
you're not supposed to start
and when is it considered like you that when you do start
though you don't have to interrupt? So when is it considered like
you started? How much starting is starting that you could say oh
I already started I don't have to interrupt? So when did you
begin the haircut? אמר רב אבין משיניח מעפורת של ספרים על ברכיו
Amar Rav Avin mishi-yaniach maphores shel saparim al birkav
when he put the blanket or whatever the mat the towel of
the barbers on your lap. Basically when they put the apron around
you even if they haven't started snipping they put the apron around
you you're in the chair you've started. Now you don't have to
interrupt. Okay. ומאימתי התחלת מרחץ? ume'eimasai hat-chalas merchatz?
When are you considered to begin the bathing the bathhouse that you
don't have to interrupt if you began? אמר רב אבין משיערים מעפורתו
הימנו Amar Rav Avin mishi'arim maphorto heimenu
when you take your handkerchief, the men used to wear head coverings,
off. So when you take off your first article of clothing, not
when you're stripped in total, when you've removed your first article of
clothing then you've started. ומאימתי התחלת בורסקי? Ume'eimatai hat-chos bursti?
When does the tanning process begin, that you're now involved in it?
משיקשור בין כתפיו. misheyikshor bein kesefav. When you tie up around your
shoulders, which I found means like you would wear an apron, like
a leather apron, right, and when you would put on the apron.
ומאימתי התחלת אכילה, Ume'eimatai hat-chos achila,
when does eating begin? So not even before you put the first
bite in your mouth. רב אמר משיטול ידיו, Rav amar misheyitol yadav,
when you've washed your hands, okay. רבי חנינא אמר משישרי חגורה, Rabbi
Chanina amar misheyatir chagura,
when you sit down and you loosen your belt. So they were
getting ready for a nice big meal, רש"י Rashi says they had
very tight belts, and therefore what do you do, you're getting ready,
so you haven't put a piece in your mouth, but you've begun
the process. לא פליגי, Lo pligi, and they're not really arguing. הא
לן והא להו. Ha lan v-ha l'hu. That's for people in ישראל,
Yisrael, that's for people in בבל. Bavel. In ישראל, Yisrael, they would
not, according to רש"י, Rashi, wear their belts so tight, so for
them it wouldn't be this idea of you sit down you loosen
your belt. For them it would begin when you washed your hands.
For בבל, Bavel, they would have tight belts, maybe even before you
washed your hands, just loosening your belt.
This is a style differential we're talking about,
yeah, but whether they wore tight belts, right, exactly.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
הני חברן בבלאי, hani chavran Bavla'ei, out
these Babylonian colleagues of ours, למאן דאמר, l-man d-amar, not exactly sure
what he means by that but okay, obviously people in בבל Bavel
but exactly what that phrase means. למאן דאמר תפילת ערבית רשות. L-man
d-amar tfilas arvis reshus. Now this is fascinating. We learned all of
ברכות Brachos about a debate whether תפילת ערבית tfilas arvis was רשות
reshus or חובה. chova. The גמרא Gemara never fully spelled out the
implications of what it means רשות. reshus. Really, if I don't want
to דאוון daven מעריב Maariv tonight, I don't have to? So you
know תוספות and everybody says no, no it doesn't really mean רשות,
reshus, it just means it's not as obligatory as חובה. chova. Technical
differences whether they say it was a רשות, reshus, it's no longer
רשות. reshus. Anyway, what's fascinating is that the גמרא Gemara there didn't
really explore the full parameters of that and some of the key
conversation winds up being here in שבת. Shabbos. So this is just
why you have to learn all of ש"ס Shas before you can
know any part of it. Anyway, so according to those that say
מעריב Maariv is a רשות, reshus, כיון דשרי להו, keivan d-sharrei lahenne,
you come home, you haven't
דאוונד davened מעריב Maariv yet, you're sitting down to your meal, and
as soon as you loosen your belt, and you're getting like now
started with the meal, ומטריחינן ליה, uma-tchinnan leh, we're not going to
bother you to go דאוון daven מעריב Maariv now. Now, does he
really mean you don't have to דאוון מעריב Maariv at all, or
does he mean we don't make you now interrupt? Maybe you'll דאוון
מעריב Maariv after you eat, okay. But at least we're not going
to ask you to interrupt once you've loosened your belt. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, but one minute, we just said the same
thing about מנחה. Once you started, we don't interrupt. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולמאן דאמר חובה מטריחינן ליה? u-l-man d-amar chova mat-chinnan leh?
So if it's an obligation, we would make you interrupt. But that's
exactly what our משנה Mishnah says, ותפילת מנחה וכולי עלמא חובה, v-tfilas
mincha v-kulei alma chova, מנחה
everybody agrees is an obligation, ותנן מתחילה אין מפסיקין. v-snan mi-techilu ein
mafsikin.
If you begin you don't interrupt, and we said begin means you've
loosened your belt. So how is מעריב Maariv different from מנחה? ואמר
רבי חנינא משישרי חגורה, V-amar Rabbi Chanina misheyatir chagura,
that beginning means loosening your belt. So if that's true about מנחה,
you don't interrupt, why is מעריב—what Maariv makes מעריב Maariv any more
lenient? Let's just read the answer. גמרא Gemara says התם לא שכיחא
שכרות הכא שכיחא שכרות. hasam lo sh-chicha shichrus hacha sh-chicha shichrus. There
you're not likely to get drunk. People don't start drinking at מנחה,
you've got work left in the day. מעריב Maariv already at evening
you take a couple of glasses of wine with your meal because
you're going to go to sleep afterwards. So if it—if מעריב Maariv
was חובה, chova, we'd make you interrupt. Why would we make you
interrupt? So that we'd be afraid you would not do it. But
if it's a רשות, reshus, even though we know you might get
drunk and not do it, we're not going to make you interrupt.
Now that is because it'll only be רשות, reshus, right? Or you—it's
common.
Now that's an amazing—that's a fascinating statement because that says that if
מעריב Maariv is a רשות, reshus, we can make our peace with
the idea that you might not actually say it. So that makes
it sound like maybe we could actually just skip מעריב Maariv if
it's a רשות. reshus. Do we really say that? So okay, thank
you.
Okay, so let's just read—I just want to read one more line
in the גמרא Gemara and then tell you what תוספות says about
this. אינמי, Inami, or the גמרא gemara says, I'm sorry, במנחה כיון
דקביע ליה זימנא מרתת ולא אתי למפשע. b-Mincha keivan d-kavi'a leh zimna
mirsas v-lo asi l-mifsha.
מנחה since there's a fixed time, there's like what we were saying
before about the רמ"א. Rama. מנחה has to get דאוונד davened within
a certain time, so you're going to be very on top of
it and you won't be negligent. ערבית כיון דכולי לילא זמן ערבית,
Arvis keivan d-kulei leilya zman arvis,
מעריב Maariv you have 12 hours in front of you, you have
the whole night ahead of you to דאוון at 3 AM. So
לא מרתת, lo mirsas, you're not afraid, ואתי למפשע, v-asi l-mifsha, and
you will come to be negligent. So the upshot of this is
that if we're afraid like I told you in the משנה Mishnah
that you're going to not do it, that you're going to run
out of time, you'll get drunk, you're not going to do it,
we will make you interrupt. So by מעריב, Maariv, if we were
afraid you'd get drunk or you'd be negligent, we would make you
interrupt, because if you're going to—might not do it, we would interrupt
you. But if it's only a רשות, reshus, that'll be okay, we're
not going to get so anxious. So how—what does that mean? Does
it mean if it's a רשות reshus you really don't have to?
So I just want to read you one line of תוספות and
with this we'll end. Look at תוספות למאן דאמר תפילת ערבית רשות,
Tosafos l-man d-amar tfilas arvis reshus, he says...
The first line near the end of that: ונראה לרי אפילו למאן
דאמר תפילת ערבית רשות אין לבטלה בחינם. v'nireh l'ri afilu l'man d'amar
tefillas arvis reshus ein l'vatlah b'chinam. Doesn't mean you just blow it
off. אלא בשביל שום צורך. ella bishvil shum tzorech. If you've got
a reason, כמו בשאר הנאה דהכא, kemo bish'ar hana'ah dehacha, like you're
in the middle of a meal. So it's true, you might wind
up missing it, but it would be a טרחא tircha to ask
you to interrupt your meal. Or in יש שום מצוה שאינו עובר
יעשה המצוה, yeish shum mitzvah she'eino over ya'aseh hamitzvah, let's say you're
involved in some other מצוה, mitzvah, you don't have to worry that,
"Oh, I'm involved in this מצוה, mitzvah, I might come to miss
מעריב." maariv. If מעריב maariv is רשות, reshus, you go ahead and
you keep on doing the מצוה mitzvah you're doing, even if you
could do the מצוה mitzvah another time, you don't have to worry
cause מעריב maariv is only a רשות. reshus. So he says, he
takes the גמרא gemara כפשוטו, kipshuto, or he basically says yeah, it
doesn't mean you can blow it off, but it does mean that
you don't have to worry about it so much. So if you're
in the middle of a meal, even if by not interrupting you
might forget about it and you might get drunk, it's fine, it's
only a רשות. reshus. Or if you're doing something important, you're doing
some מצוה, mitzvah, even if you could do it some other time,
don't have to worry cause מעריב maariv is only a רשות. reshus.
Now, as I said, people don't leave it at this, and what
they basically wind up saying is as the רמב״ם Rambam says whatever,
it might have started once it was a רשות, reshus, now we've
accepted it as a חובה. chovah. So any of these discussions of
the גמרא gemara. are more theoretical, but it is interesting that a
primary discussion of מעריב maariv being a רשות reshus occurs here in
the גמרא.